R. Wolfenden & Sons Photographs on the Dyeing Process 6896/014 P
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
R. Wolfenden & Sons Photographs on the Dyeing Process
1950
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Stevens Companies
R. Wolfenden & Sons
American Textile History Museum
6896/014 P
0.33 cubic feet
A series of 24 photographs depicting the dyeing process from beginning to end.
0.3 linear ft.
Gelatin silver print, photographs.
10064287
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Biographical / Historical
In 1868 Robert Wolfenden founded the Attleborough Dye Works. Around 1878 he brought his two sons, John W. and Oscar, into the business as partners. It was not until Robert Wolfenden's death that the name of the company was changed to R. Wolfenden & Sons.
By 1930 the company had one of the largest, if not largest, plants in the world that does nothing but dye textiles. At that time they employed about 175 people and could dye 25 tons of fabric per day.
R. Wolfenden and Sons became a division of J.P. Stevens & Co. in 1949.
Scope and Contents
Images depict, step-by-step, the dyeing process in a 24 photograph series. The series was made circa 1950. Also includes one other photograph of an employee at a drying machine, which is not numbered, but appears to be part of the series.
Custodial History
American Textile History Museum Collection
Related Materials
Related Collections: 6896: Stevens Companies Records 6896 AV: Stevens Companies Audio-Visual 6896 F: Stevens Companies Films 6896 G: Stevens Companies Graphics 6896 LS: Stevens Companies Glass Lantern Slides 6896 MB: Stevens Companies Memorabilia 6896 OH: Stevens Companies Oral Histories 6896 P: Stevens Companies Photographs 6896 PUBS: Stevens Companies Publications 6896/001: Stevens Companies Correspondence 6896/002: Stevens Companies Legal Documents 6896/003: M.T. Stevens & Sons Company Records 6896/004: J.P. Stevens and Company Records 6896/005: Andover Mills Records 6896/006: Fitchburg Worsted Company Records 6896/007: Hockanum Mills and American Mills Records 6896/008: Montello Woolen Mills Records 6896/009: Oslo Woolen Mill Records 6896/010: Pentucket Mills Records 6896/011: Richmond Worsted Company Records 6896/012: Stevens Linen Works Records 6896/013: Stevens Mills of North Andover Records 6896/015: Stevens Family Papers 6896/016: Augustus G. Stevens Papers 6896/017: B. W. Couch Papers 6896/018: Carl Vetter Papers 6896/019: Daniel J. Gannon, Sr. Papers 6896/020: John H. McGarrigle Papers 6896/021: Phliip A. Johnson Papers 6896/022: Richard S. Parker Papers
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives 227 Ives Hall Tower Road Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheelref@cornell.edu https://catherwood.library.cornell.edu/kheel/
Compiled by:
R. Miles, October 10, 2017
EAD encoding:
Randall Miles, December 06, 2017
Dyes and dyeing; Textile fabrics; Textile machinery; Textile research; Textile workers; Winding machines; Women textile workers; Yarn; Industries -- Massachusetts -- Attleboro; J.P. Stevens & Co.; R. Wolfenden & Sons (Attleboro, Mass.); American Textile History Museum
10064287
- Textile chemist preparing a dye solution, ATHM# 0000.1488.17, 1950; black and white photograph; 25.25 x 20.75 cm. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  Gelatin silver print. Image depicts a female employee preparing a dye solution in an office in the company. Bottles of dyes and solutions on table and windowsill; spools of thread on table. Number 1 in a series of photographs on the dyeing process.
- Employee at a mixing tank, ATHM# 0000.1488.19, 1950; black and white photograph; 20.5 x 25.25 cm. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Gelatin silver print. Image depicts a male employee at a mixing tank. The dye solution is made up in the tank. A powered agitator stirs the mix. The employee's scoop probably contains sizing. no.2 in a series of photographs on the dyeing process.
- Employee adding size mix to the dye applicator's bath, ATHM# 0000.1488.18, 1950; black and white photograph; 20.5 x 25.5 cm. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Gelatin silver print. Image depicts a male employee (see also items 16-18 in this folder for views of this worker) adding size mix to the dye applicator's bath. A size mixture would make the yarn smoother and stronger to stand the strain of weaving. Number 3 in a series of photographs on the dyeing process.
- Dye kettle and dye applicator, ATHM# 0000.1488.7, 1950; black and white photograph; 25.75 x 20.25 cm. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Gelatin silver print. Image depicts a dye kettle or dye tank in the foreground, where the dye solution is stored. On the right is a dye applicator. Number 4 in a series of photographs on the dyeing process.
- Pressure dye tank, ATHM# 0000.1488.6, 1950; black and white photograph; 25.75 x 20.25 cm. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Gelatin silver print. Image depicts a pressure dye tank or kettle in which yarn packages are dyed. Number 5 in a series of photographs on the dyeing process.
- Employee at dye kettle, ATHM# 0000.1488.5, 1950; black and white photograph; 28 x 21.75 cm. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Gelatin silver print. Image depicts a male employee working at a dye kettle. The operator is working the controls for lifting the dyed yarn on the tray out of the dye kettle. Number 6 in a series of photographs on the dyeing process.
- Dyeing machinery, ATHM# 0000.1488.3, 1950; black and white photograph; 28 x 22 cm. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Gelatin silver print. Image depicts a dye kettle (left), dye tank (right) and dyeing controls with recorders (center). Dyed spools of yarn are being lifted out of the dye kettle on the left. Number 7 in a series of photographs on the dyeing process.
- Close-up view of interior of a dye vat, ATHM# 0000.1488.4, 1950; black and white photograph; 25.5 x 20.75 cm. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Gelatin silver print. Image depicts the interior of a dye vat or dye kettle. The heating coils and the circulator pump are located at the bottom of the kettle where the dye is stored and then pumped to the adjacent package dye machine. Number 8 in a series of photographs on the dyeing process.
- Yarn packages on a package tray for dyeing, ATHM# 0000.1488.2, 1950; black and white photograph; 25.5 x 20.5 cm. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Gelatin silver print. Image depicts a close-up view of spools of yarn on a package tray to be dyed. The yarns are wound on dye-tubes or cloth-covered springs to form a dye package; the packages are then stacked on the tray spindles (shown here). The tray is then fed into the dye kettle and the cover closed and sealed before the dye is pumped into the kettle. Number 9 in a series of photographs on the dyeing process.
- Package dyeing, ATHM# 0000.1488.1, 1950; black and white photograph; 25.5 x 20.5 cm. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Gelatin silver print. Image depicts a close-up view of spools of yarn in a dye vat. The kettle is loaded with dye packages on the tray. The image here shows the retainers on the top of the spindles. Number 10 in a series of photographs on the dyeing process.
- Female employees at spooler, ATHM# 0000.1488.13, 1950; black and white photograph; 24 x 19.5 cm. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Gelatin silver print. Image depicts three female employees at work at a spooling machine. The spooling machine winds the yarn onto cones. Number 11 in a series of photographs on the dyeing process.
- Employee hanging skeins to dry, ATHM# 0000.1488.10, 1950; black and white photograph; 25.5 x 20.5 cm. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Gelatin silver print. Image depicts a male employee removing dyed skeins of yarn and hanging them on a wooden rod, probably to dry. Number 12 in a series of photographs on the dyeing process.
- Employees scouring skein warps, ATHM# 0000.1488.9, 1950; black and white photograph; 20.5 x 25.5 cm. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Gelatin silver print. Image depicts two male employees at a scouring machine, where the skeins are being scoured to remove any oils, dirt, etc. no.13 in a series of photographs on the dyeing process.
- Employee at a hydro-extractor, ATHM# 0000.1488.8, 1950; black and white photograph; 20.5 x 25.25 cm. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Gelatin silver print. Image depicts a male employee at a hydro-extractor. Fabric (or yarn) is placed in the perforated basket, which is then spun (using centrifugal force) at a sufficient speed as to force the excess liquid through the sides of the basket. Fabric or yarn so treated thereby requires less time in a dryer or tenter. Number 14 in a series of photographs on the dyeing process.
- Employee winding the skeins, ATHM# 0000.1488.11, 1950; black and white photograph; 20.5 x 25.25 cm. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Gelatin silver print. Image depicts a female employee in the foreground straightening the dyed skeins of yarn; in the background, another female employee winds the skeins on a winder. Number 15 in a series of photographs on the dyeing process.
- Piece dyeing, ATHM# 0000.1488.15, 1950; black and white photograph; 25.5 x 20.5 cm. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Gelatin silver print. Image depicts male employee examining fabric that has been dyed (piece dyeing, or dyeing of finished fabric as opposed to dyeing skeins of yarn or cones). See items 3, 17, and 18 in this folder for other views of piece dyeing with the same employee pictured. Number 16 in a series of photographs on the dyeing process.
- Piece dyeing, ATHM# 0000.1488.14, 1950; black and white photograph; 25.5 x 20.5 cm. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Gelatin silver print. Image depicts male employee examining fabric that has been dyed (piece dyeing, or dyeing of finished fabric as opposed to dyeing skeins of yarn or cones). See items 3, 16, and 18 in this folder for other views of piece dyeing with the same employee pictured. Number 17 in a series of photographs on the dyeing process.
- Checking dyed fabric, ATHM# 0000.1488.16, 1950; black and white photograph; 25.5 x 20.5 cm. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Gelatin silver print. Image depicts male employee examining fabric that has been dyed (piece dyeing, or dyeing of finished fabric as opposed to dyeing skeins of yarn or cones). See items 3, 18, and 17 in this folder for other views of piece dyeing with the same employee pictured. Number 18 in a series of photographs on the dyeing process.
- Open width cloth scouring, ATHM# 0000.1488.20, 1950; black and white photograph; 25.5 x 20.5 cm. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Gelatin silver print. Image depicts a male employee at cloth scouring machine. An immersion tank is at the bottom. Cloth then passes upward through squeeze rolls to remove the excess liquid. A safety guard keeps the tender's fingers away from the squeeze rolls. See item 20 in this folder for a close-up view of this procedure. Number 19 in a series of photographs on the dyeing process.
- Close-up view of open width cloth scouring, ATHM# 0000.1488.21, 1950; black and white photograph; 20.5 x 25.5 cm. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Gelatin silver print. Image depicts a cloth scouring machine. Cloth is immersed in a prepared solution in the tank at the bottom. Cloth then passes upward through squeeze rolls to remove the excess liquid. A metal safety guard keeps the tender's fingers away from the squeeze rolls. Number 20 in a series of photographs on the dyeing process.
- Close-up view of immersion tank and squeeze rolls, ATHM# 0000.1488.22, 1950; black and white photograph; 20.5 x 25.5 cm. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Gelatin silver print. Image depicts a close-up view of the immersion tank and squeeze rolls used in cloth scouring. The cloth is immersed in a prepared solution in the immersion tank. The squeeze rolls squeeze out excess liquid; the metal safety guard keeps the tender's fingers away from the squeeze rolls. Number 21 in a series of photographs on the dyeing process.
- Employee inspecting cloth from dryer, ATHM# 0000.1488.25, 1950; black and white photograph; 20.5 x 25.5 cm. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Gelatin silver print. Image depicts a male employee checking cloth as it comes off the drying machine and is loosely folded onto a movable pallet. Number 22 in a series of photographs on the dyeing process.
- Open width dryer, ATHM# 0000.1488.24, 1950; black and white photograph; 25.5 x 20.5 cm. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Gelatin silver print. Image depicts a male employee operating an open width dryer, where cloth is being dried and folded. Number 23 in a series of photographs on the dyeing process.
- Employee with finished bales of cloth for shipping, ATHM# 0000.1488.26, 1950; black and white photograph; 25.25 x 20.5 cm. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Gelatin silver print. Image depicts a male employee moving a load of finished bales of cloth into an area holding other bales, possibly a shipping room. no.24 in a series of photographs on the dyeing process.
- View of drying machine, ATHM# 00001488.23, 1950; black and white photograph; 25.5 x 20.5 cm. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Gelatin silver print. Image depicts a view of a male employee at a drying machine where finished cloth is being dried. Unnumbered but part of a series of photographs on the dyeing process.